ACTWU's Operations Department's Records on the Sidney Hillman Awards 5619/009
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Operations Department's Records on the Sidney Hillman Awards
1947-1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Operations Department
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Operations Department
5619/009
2 cubic feet
2 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of correspondence, reports, and files from the Operations Department regarding the Sidney Hillman Awards. Prominent in this collection are materials related to the award luncheons and biographies of union officers.
6764533
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
February 17, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America And all other 5619 collections.
Textile industry--New York (State)--New York; Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York; Clothing trade--New York (State)--New York; Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Operations Department; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees --Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
6764533
- Sidney Hillman Foundation [folder 1 of 2], 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sidney Hillman Foundation [folder 2 of 2], 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hillman Health Center 40th Anniversary Luncheon, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  October 18, 1991.
- Bernstein Award, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Sidney Hillman, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Invitations, Plaques, Programs, Seating, Ads
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Bills
- Materials for Jay Mazur (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hillman Biography. Steve Fraser, Photographer (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hillman Foundation. Rieve-Pollock Foundation (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hillman Awards and Luncheon, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Hillman Awards, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Invitation, Program, Scrolls, Ad, Posting
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Hillman Awards Luncheon, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Correspondence, Biographies, Scripts, Articles
- Hillman Conference Material, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  June 26, 1989.
- ILGWU/ACTWU Merger Articles, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- The Institute for Urban Family Health, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Hillman Stamp (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Sidney Hillman (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Hillman Awards (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Minutes. Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1947-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Minutes. Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1966-1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Administration of Hillman Foundation Prize Award Program, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- 1992 Hillman Awards (Box 1, Folder 29)
- 1992 Hillman Awards Luncheon (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Sidney Hillman Foundation (Box 1, Folder 31)
- 1991 Sidney Hillman Awards (Box 1, Folder 32)
- 1992 TV Award (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1992 Awards. AFL. CIO, Exec Council Mailing, GEB (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Correspondence, Memos
- Biographies. Other Unions (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Biographies. Vice Presidents (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Biography. Sol Stetin (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Biographies. Joint Board Members (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Biographies. A to D (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Biographies. E to L (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Biographies. M to Z (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Biography. Scott M. Hoyman (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Biography. Murray H. Finley (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Biography. Joyce Miller (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Biography. Arthur Loevy (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Old Biographies. A to L (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Old Biographies. M to Z (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Biographies. Deceased (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Biography. Sidney Hillman (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Biography. Esther Peterson (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Biography. Jacob S. Potofsky (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Biography. Jack Rubenstein (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Biography. Charles Sallee (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Biography. Jack Sheinkman (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Old Biography. Jack Sheinkman (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Jack Sheinkman DNR Photos, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Sol Stetin (Box 2, Folder 26)
- UNITE! Logos (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Press Release Materials (Box 2, Folder 28)
- ACWA & TWUA Logos (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Anniversary Celebration Logos ('75 & '50) ACWA and Textile (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Merger Articles, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Sidney Hillman Press Release, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Biography. Jay Mazur, President of UNITE! (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Biography. Susan Cowell (Box 2, Folder 34)